Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America PE.007
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America
1936-1994
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.007
3.75 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons, 1 oversize shared box, and 1 shared manuscript box
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE) (1936-1994) is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. After the American Federation of Labor declined to grant a charter to the UE, it became the first union chartered under the newly formed Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO). The UE collection consists primarily of agreements, contracts, and constitutions, as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, brochures, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and publications. Materials in this collection date from the 1930s to the 1990s, and include files from late 1940s and early 1950s which document the UE's disaffiliation with the CIO.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE) (1936-1994) consists of agreements, contracts, and constitutions, as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, brochures, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and other publications. A sizable portion of the collection is made up of pamphlets put out by the UE on a number of different topics, including civil rights, communism, wages, record keeping, union busting, and women's rights. The pamphlets are arranged chronologically by decade. Ranging in date from the founding of the UE in 1936 to the 1990s, the material in this collection was generated by the national and international bodies of the UE. The collection also contains agreements, fliers, pamphlets and other printed ephemera put out by UEs various districts and locals.
Historical
The United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America, also known as the UE, was formed in 1936. After the American Federation of Labor declined to grant a charter to the UE, it became the first union chartered under the newly formed Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO). The UE saw a growth in membership during the war years to more than 300,000 members. In 1949 the UE left the CIO in response to the latter's anti-communism activities. The CIO went on to establish the International Union of Electrical Workers (IUE) as a rival union. The UE tried to rebuild its membership throughout the 1960s and 1970s, however this was difficult and continued to be as membership was hit hard by closing plants in the 1980s. As of 2009, the UE continues to practice what it refers to "rank and file unionism" and remains unaffiliated with the AFL-CIO.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series. Folders are arranged alphabetically within series. The series arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I: National Union Files, 1936-1994
Series II: District and Local Files, 1940-1979
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. There is no accession record associated with this collection.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; Press releases.; Pamphlets.; Hearings (event); Bulletins.; Speeches.; Reports.; Publications (documents); Circular letters.; Constitutions.; Printed ephemera.; Fliers (printed matter); Testimonies.; Agreements.; Articles.; Labor unions and communism -- United States.; Labor unions; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America
- Series I: National Union Files, 1936-1994; 2.75 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 1 shared oversize box, and 1 shared manuscript box
  - Agreements and Contracts I, 1944- (Box 1)
  - Agreements and Contracts II, 1944- (Box 1)
  - Brochures, 1938-1982, undated (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 5)
  - Circular Letters, 1948-1994, undated (Box 1)
  - Civil Rights, 1951-1965 (Box 1)
  - Communism, 1953, undated (Box 1)
  - Conferences: National Conference on Problems of Working Women, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Conferences: World Trade Union Conference, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, 1936-1979 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, 1980-1996 (Box 1)
  - Convention photograph, 1914 (Box Shared Tamiment 017, Folder 10)
  - Conventions, 1939-1944 (Box 1)
  - Conventions, 1947-1962 (Box 1)
  - Conventions, 1965-1975 (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 6)
  - Conventions, 1976-1979 (Box 1)
  - Conventions, 1980-1988 (Box 1)
  - Conventions, 1989-1996 (Box 1)
  - Fliers and Ephemera I, 1940s-1990s, undated (Box 1)
  - Fliers and Ephemera II, 1940s-1990s, undated (Box 1)
  - Hearings/Testimonies, 1948-1954 (Box 1)
  - Minimum Wage: Briefs on, 1939-1941 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles on, 1938-1990, undated (Box 1)
  - "On the Air": Radio Broadcasts, 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Organizer's Bulletin, 1951-1959, undated (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets, 1930-1939, undated (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets I, 1940-1949 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets II, 1940-1949 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets, 1950-1959 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets, 1960-1969 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets, 1968-1979 (Box 2, Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 7)
  - Pamphlets I, 1980-1989 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets II, 1980-1989 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets, 1990- (Box 2)
  - Plastic Workers Organizing Committee (Erie, PA), undated (Box 2)
  - Press Releases, 1957, undated (Box 2)
  - Publications (Various Bulletins and other Serial Publications), 1947-1966, undated (Box 2)
  - Rank and File Activities, undated (Box 2)
  - Reports, 1948-1959 (Box 2)
  - Speeches and Statements, 1957-1970 (Box 2)
  - Stewards: Guides and Manuals, 1937-1973 (Box 2)
- Series II: District and Local Files, 1940-1979; 2 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons
  - District 4, 1942-1944, undated (Box 2)
  - District 7, 1953-1971, undated (Box 2)
  - District 8, 1949, undated (Box 2)
  - District 11, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Local 155, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Local 207: Agreements and Contracts, 1945-1946 (Box 2)
  - Local 209: Constitution, undated (Box 2)
  - Local 227: Agreements and Contracts, 1945-1950 (Box 2)
  - Local 229: Agreements and Contracts, 1946-1947 (Box 2)
  - Local 230: Agreements and Contracts, 1947-1950 (Box 2)
  - Local 232: Agreements and Contracts, 1946-1947 (Box 2)
  - Local 237: Agreements and Contracts I, 1942-1959 (Box 3)
  - Local 237: Agreements and Contracts II, 1942-1959 (Box 3)
  - Local 237: Constitutions, undated (Box 3)
  - Local 243: Agreements and Contracts I, 1947-1986 (Box 3)
  - Local 243: Agreements and Contracts II, 1947-1986 (Box 3)
  - Local 243: Agreements and Contracts III, 1947-1986 (Box 3)
  - Local 247: Agreements and Contracts, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Local 249: Agreements and Contracts, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Local 251: Agreements and Contracts, 1946 (Box 3)
  - Local 284, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Local 293: Agreements and Contracts, 1947-1948 (Box 3)
  - Local 299, circa 1980s (Box 3)
  - Local 425, 1941 (Box 3)
  - Local 427: Agreements and Contracts, 1946 (Box 3)
  - Local 430, 1952 (Box 3)
  - Local 450: Agreements and Contracts, 1943 (Box 3)
  - Local 456: Agreements and Contracts, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Local 475, undated (Box 3)
  - Local 510, 1940 (Box 3)
  - Local 601 (Pittsburgh, PA), 1945-1949 (Box 3)
  - Local 613, undated (Box 3)
  - Local 751 (Niles, OH), undated (Box 3)
  - Local 813: Agreements and Contracts, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Local 1114, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Local 1210, undated (Box 3)